Okay בוקר טוב. boker tov. So today's דף daf is כ"ה, chaf-hey,
we're sort of at the bottom of כ"ה, chaf-hey, so we'll hopefully
get about a half a דף daf ahead, so we'll be able
to finish on Sunday. And we pick up in the middle of
כ"ה עמוד א': chaf-hey amud aleph: ובשעת הגיתות נאמנים על התרומה. U'bishat
hagisos ne'emanim al hatruma. So now we are starting to get to,
ah, שכוייח, sh-koach, we're starting to get to ways in which place
times at which the עמי הארץ amei ha-aretz are believed and these
distinctions are done away with. And one of them is in יהודה
Yehuda they're believed about קודש, kodesh, only in יהודה Yehuda because it's
near the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. And then in all places they're
believed about תרומה truma at the time of the pressing of the
grapes and of the olives. Partly רש"י Rashi says it's based on
certain facts on the ground that people, you know, because it was
the beginning of a whole season, everybody went and took all their
vessels to the מקווה mikva and so on, so there was a
greater assumption that everybody was doing it in טהרה. tahara. And also
as רש"י Rashi is going to say in a little bit, because
otherwise you would be excluding כהנים kohanim from the ability to get
all this תרומה, truma, כהנים kohanim who are חברים. chaveirim. So there
was a certain policy, so you know, social policy in place particularly
from the perspective of the חברים chaveirim to ensure that this would
be a time where you could believe people. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this: ובשעת הגיתות נאמנים על התרומה. U'bishat hagisos ne'emanim al
hatruma. ורמינהי, Vermini, I'll ask you on this: הגומר זיתו ישייר קופה
אחת ויתננה לעני כהן. Ha-gomair zeiso yeshayair kupa achas ve-yitnena le-ani kohein.
That somebody who finishes his, you know, pressing his olives, should leave
over one, one, you know, basket of unpressed olives and give it
to a poor כהן kohein who in parenthesis is a חבר. chaver.
What does it mean why shouldn't he press the olives? Because unpressed
olives don't have liquid come in contact with them and are not
susceptible for becoming טמא. tamei. So basically what it's saying is, here
you are an עם הארץ, am ha-aretz, you want to give your
תרומה truma to a כהן kohein who's a חבר. chaver. Here's the
advice. The advice is, don't give it after it's become olive oil,
after it's become, you know, grape juice or you know, pre-fermented wine,
give it to them in the form of olives and grapes before
it's come in contact with liquid and then it won't be susceptible
for טומאה, tuma, right, but okay. And then they'll be able to
accept it. So anyway the upshot is is that you're not believed
on טומאה וטהרה tuma ve-tahara even at the time of the pressing
of the olives and the grapes. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רב נחמן לא קשיא הא בחרפי הא באפלי. Amar Rav Nachman lo
kashya ha be-charfei ha be-aflei. Depends whether we're dealing with early or
late. If basically we're dealing here with that this was a late
harvest of the olives and therefore when you were getting around to
pressing it it was no longer the normal season of pressing and
therefore it was a time period when you would not be believed,
you the עם הארץ. am ha-aretz. But that's an exception, it's not
a general rule. אמרו ליה רב אדא בר אבא כגון מאי? Amrei
lei Rav Adda bar Abba kegon mai? What would be an example?
כגון הני דבית אביך, kegon oseinu shel beis avicha, like your father's,
your father's has a presumably an olive orchard and his stuff always
ripens late and his stuff always is ready for pressing after the
time of the pressing. Okay, that's one answer. רב יוסף אמר בגליל
שנו. Rav Yosef amrei be-Galila shanu. We're talking about in the גליל.
Galil. Now to say it's בגליל שנו, be-Galila shanu, that it's interesting,
it means that even on the issue of תרומה truma and the
time of oil pressing of the pressing there's a difference between Judea
and the גליל. Galil. Now we understood before why they made a
difference for קודש kodesh because only in יהודה Yehuda were they able
to get to the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash so there was a
different context for the aspects of קודש kodesh than in the גליל.
Galil. But why by תרומה truma should it make a difference? So
let's see what the גמרא Gemara says about this.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this: אמיתיבי אביי, Amseiba Abaye, אביי
Abaye asks on this, we have a ברייתא: braisa: עבר הירדן והגליל
הרי הן כיהודה, Ever Hayarden ve-ha-Galil harei hein ke-Yehuda, the Trans-Jordan area
and the גליל Galil
they're just like יהודה Yehuda for תרומה truma purposes. נאמנים על היין
בשעת היין ועל השמן בשעת השמן. Ne'emanim al hayayin bishat hayayin ve-al
hashemen bishat hashemen. They're believed that the wine is טהור tahor when
it's the time of pressing wine and that the oil is טהור
tahor when it's the time of pressing oil. ולא על השמן בשעת
היין ולא על היין בשעת השמן, ve-lo al hashemen bishat hayayin ve-lo
al hayayin bishat hashemen,
but not when it's the pressing season for the other thing. But
when it's their own pressing season people are believed to say it's
טהור tahor for תרומה truma not only for קודש kodesh for תרומה
truma and even in the גליל. Galil. אלא מחוורתא כדשנינן מעיקרא. Ela
mechvarta kedishni me'ikara.
The first answer was better, was it an exception it wasn't exactly
the right normal season that's why it was a problem but the
clear principle here is that this belief that everybody is believed about
תרומה truma at the time of pressing is regardless of geographical location.
Okay so here we have that in addition to the idea of
believability by קודש kodesh in general, Joe good to see you back
you doing okay?
Okay. All right. So in addition to believability around תרומה truma in
all locations at the time that it's being pressed at the time
when it's most urgent to be believed about it. עברו הגיתות ועברו,
Avra hagisos ve-avruto, if this time passes over, והביא לו חבית של
יין, ve-heivi lo chavis shel yayin,
and an עם הארץ am ha-aretz brings to a חבר chaver a
barrel of wine, לא יקבל הימנו, lo yikabel menu, he shouldn't accept
it. He shouldn't accept it הימנו. hemennu. I can't take it now
because I can't believe you now, and I'll be stuck with תרומה
טמאה. truma tmea. אבל מניחה לגת הבאה, Aval manichah le-gat ha-baah, says,
you know what, do me a favor, hold on to it and
bring it back to me like ten months from now at the
next time of the pressing season and then I'll be able to
believe you. Even though it's the exact same barrel. We're going to
see something just like this coming up later also. Where he'd have
even more opportunity to become טמא. tamei. Well, that is a good
point. So, it's an excellent point actually. Okay, so בעי מיניה מרב
ששת, Ba'ei minei me-Rav Sheshet, they asked רב ששת. Rav Sheshet. It's
abstracted into a formality. Exactly, exactly. עבר וקבלה מהו שיניחנה לגת הבאה?
Avar ve-kiblah mahu she-yanichennah le-gat ha-baah?
Let's say the כהן חבר Kohen chaver accepted the barrel of wine
or oil and he didn't say bring it back to me. So
is he now allowed to hold onto it for till the next
pressing season and then say, now here it is now ten months
from now, oh yeah ten months ago the guy told me it
was טהור, tahor, now I can believe him? And then he can
make it טהור. tahor. So can he hold onto it and then
it'll change its status? אמר להו, Amar lehu, so he said to
them, תניתוה, tenisuha, we taught it. חבר ועם הארץ Chaver ve-am ha-aretz
שירשו את אביהם, she-yarshu es avihem, חבר ועם הארץ chaver ve-am ha-aretz
excuse me, שירשו את אביהם. she-yarshu es avihem.
So now what happens is the following: a חבר chaver and an
עם הארץ am ha-aretz both have, their father passed away, and their
father was עם הארץ. am ha-aretz. Their father himself was an עם
הארץ. am ha-aretz. So their father left behind all of these wine
and grapes and olives and grain and all this stuff. The problem
is is that because he was an עם הארץ, am ha-aretz, a
חבר chaver would have to assume that all of that is טמא.
tamei. Okay,
now you have his sons, one of them actually went ahead and
became a חבר. chaver. The other one remained an עם הארץ. am
ha-aretz. Alright, so what is their story? Now, you could say okay
whatever, so you like you split it up and you deal with
the טמא tamei stuff. Well maybe there's stuff that's actually טהור tahor
that had never come in contact with liquid and maybe that's the
stuff that the חבר chaver wants, not the stuff that you know...
so I'll take the dry stuff, you take the stuff that's come
in contact with liquid. So here's the problem: the problem is is
that if you say that we are like equal partners in everything,
then if I take the dry grain and you take the grain
that's been washed, what effectively we're doing is we're saying I will
give you my half of the washed grain for your half of
the dry grain. So basically I am now giving you the עם
הארץ am ha-aretz stuff that is טמא tamei in order to take
the stuff that is טהור. tahor. I'm not allowed to do that
as a חבר chaver because I'm basically leading you into sin. I
am actually giving you stuff that's טמא tamei that I know that
you're not going to be careful about observing the restrictions about it.
So a חבר chaver is not allowed to give an עם הארץ
am ha-aretz something that is already you know has is already טמא.
tamei. But the עם הארץ am ha-aretz owns it in any case,
you're not giving him anything. You're saying just take... No, but effectively
we're fifty percent owners in everything, so really we should split everything
down the middle. But we're actually saying I'd rather take the dry
stuff and you take the the washed stuff, well then it's actually
we're we're swapping our portions for the dry for the wet, so
that's a problem. You could just as easily say I'll take this
as opposed to saying you give me this. No, but
but legally what's happening is, but there is a way in which
it could be seen like it's just the natural way of splitting,
which is if it is the same מין, min, the same type
of thing that we're splitting. So let's take a look at that.
Okay, so... yeah,
yeah. So let's take a look.
יכול לומר לו, Yachol lomar lo, you can say to him, טול
אתה חטין שבמקום פלוני ואני חטין שבמקום פלוני. tol attah chittin she-bimkom
peloni va-ani chittin she-bimkom peloni. You take the the wheat you know
the wheat grain over there and I'll take the wheat grain over
here. It happens to be the one I'm giving you is the
stuff that's been washed and the one I'm taking is the stuff
that's dry. Or טול אתה יין שבמקום פלוני ואני יין שבמקום פלוני,
tol attah yayin she-bimkom peloni va-ani yayin she-bimkom peloni, or you take
the wine over there and I'll take the wine over here. Exactly
how the wine is not a problem is not exactly clear to
me but okay somehow it's in a context where you know as
the חבר chaver that the wine in a certain place was processed
in a way that was totally okay. אבל לא יאמר לו, Aval
lo yomar lo, טול אתה לח ואני יבש. tol attah lach va-ani
yavesh.
Within the same grain I can't say to you, you know what,
you just take the wet grain the stuff that's been sort of
washed and I'll take the dry one. טול אתה חטין ואני שעורין,
Tol attah chittin va-ani se'orin, or you take the the wheat and
I'll take the barley. Cause something like wheat and barley is clearly
we're switching our portions. Interesting thing is even the prior stuff, even
if it's all wheat and wheat, if I specifically designate well you
take the wet the washed wheat and I'll take the dry, that's
still seen like I'm switching my portion for you. But if it's
relatively arbitrary, you take the stuff half of his stuff is in
you know one field and half is in the other field, you
know let's just you just take the stuff over there I'll take
the stuff here, then that's just okay that's just a way of
dividing, it's not swapping. And this is on the principle of like
יש ברירה, yesh bereira, that if it's that if it's a logical
natural division, then we can say that well that was the stuff
that was always going to be yours and his was the stuff
that was always going to be his and there was no swapping
that took place. If it's what we would consider to be
a... seen as an actual sense of, you know, giving you the
the טמא tamei stuff and me taking the טהור tahor stuff, and
that would be a problem because of a type of a משנה
היא פה. Mishna hi po. Isn't he really doing that? What? In
a sense. Yeah, in a sense, in a sense it is doing
that, it's always doing that, but the question is when do we
have to sort of legally see it that way, right? When do
we just see it as like, no, you know, you had to
split it somehow, so yours is yours, that's yours, there's no swapping.
When do we see it, when do we see it as a
split and when do we see it as a swapping of my
portion for your portion? Now you're right, if we say אין ברירה
ein brera we always see it as a swap because then there's
never a pre-determined portion which is mine or yours. But if we
say יש ברירה yesh brera then it means that when it's a
natural type of a division we could see it like this was
always your part and that was always his part. When it's a
less natural type of a division then we see it as an
exchange. Okay. All right. ותניא לן, Ve-tanya lan, now we talked on
this, אותו חבר שורף את הלח ומניח את היבש. Oso chaver soreif
es ha-lach u-meniach es ha-yavesh. So this חבר chaver that if he's
a כהן, kohen, okay, and he basically gets stuff that is, that
is has come in contact with liquid or actually is liquid, but
now let's say הלח ha-lach in the case over there like the
washed grain. So what can he do with this? So it's תרומה
טמאה. truma t'mea. So he's not allowed to eat תרומה טמאה, truma
t'mea, the only thing you can do with תרומה טמאה truma t'mea
is that you burn it. Okay. ומניח את היבש U-meniach es ha-yavesh
but he doesn't have to worry about the stuff that's never been
in contact with liquid because that's טהור. tahor. All right. Now, אמאי,
amai, now here's the key question, why if it worked out that
he took, you know, he had to,
you know, he had to split it down the middle and he
had to take stuff that he had to assume was טמא tamei
that had been washed, why does he have to burn it? Why
not just יניחנו לגת הבאה? yanichenu legas ha-ba? Why not just wait
until the next pressing time, right? And then he'll be able to
believe that it was טהור. tahor. Now the interesting thing is the
person who actually knows it's טהור tahor or could make that claim
is dead, right? The father died. But the interesting thing is it
sounds like you don't even need somebody to make a claim. It
just seems to be like at the time of the pressing we
can just assume that everything is טהור. tahor. Right? We can just
assume everything is טהור tahor at the time of pressing. So you
don't even have to get the father to come back and you
know, so if the reality is that you can just assume at
that time even stuff that's already come into your possession, then why
doesn't he just wait around? Yeah, but if you know something was
pressed not in the season? No, no, it's just, right. Right. Oh,
you mean, oh you mean if it's pressed not at the season
and how formalized? Right, that's an interesting question too. Right, we are
dealing with it was pressed during the season but it wasn't delivered
until you sort of wait around till the next time. Right. You're
saying let's say it דוקא davka wasn't pressed. Well, I think that
was the phrase before by the late olives, right? Where the case
of the late olives it seemed that you didn't have another alternative.
So it seems that minimally it does have to have been pressed
during the right season, that at least there's maybe some facts that
support it. So let's see what the גמרא Gemara's answer is. אמאי
יניחנו לגת הבאה? Amai yanichenu legas ha-ba? So בדבר שאין לו גת.
Bedavar she-ein lo gas. No, maybe it's a type of a thing
that there's no season for pressing, right? Who knows what it is,
it's some type of a thing, maybe anyway it's grain and it's
washing of a grain and maybe this whole thing first of all
it's not clear that this applies to stuff that's not olive oil
and grapes, right? Which has a very particular season and you gather
it all together and there's a very limited time that everybody's working
on pressing it and so on. Something like grain obviously there's seasons
for grain but it does not have the same type of a
focused period and maybe it wasn't the same reality. So anyway there's
not even any evidence it applies to non-oil and grapes and it
wouldn't apply to something that did not have a pressing season.
Okay. ויניחנו לרגל. Ve-yanichenu laregel. Okay, what we're about to learn that
everybody's also believed on the רגל regel that the תרומה truma is
טהור. tahor. Okay and maybe again you don't have to ask anybody,
you can just assume everything is טהור tahor even and you just
wait until the רגל. regel. So בדבר שאינו משתמר לרגל. Bedavar she-eino
mishtamer laregel. All right, it's something that'll spoil. Okay, so we don't
have any evidence from that, that it says destroy it, that it
means there's no options. Maybe in theory there are options if you
wait for the גת gas or you wait for the רגל, regel,
but we'd be talking in a scenario where that's not available. So
we don't have an answer to the question of if you've actually
already received it and therefore had to assume it's טמא, tamei, maybe
you just wait till the right time and then can assume it's
טהור. tahor. Okay and presumably once you assume it's טהור tahor it
doesn't become טמא tamei again. Meaning once you wait until the next
גת gas and now you could assume it's טהור, tahor, we don't
say after that period is over it becomes טמא. tamei. Once it
gets a stamp of טהור tahor it remains that way. So it's
pretty formalist, yes. Very broad application of the idea of עם הארץ
am ha'aretz on the רגל. regel. Right? עם הארץ am ha'aretz thought
that well, if it's the רגל regel people know that they're supposed
to be טהור, tahor, so something that he's eating on the רגל
regel you can assume it's טהור, tahor, but, but, you know, six
months ago when he was preparing them he was processing it. Right.
So that's an excellent point and that gets exactly to this issue
that how much is it based on the real facts of people's
care and how much is it based on certain policy concerns that
when you get to the... That, you know, in terms of technical
הלכה Halacha we would believe people. All of these are חומרות chumros
upon חומרות chumros and we're מקל meikel them because of שמחת יום
טוב. Simchas Yom Tov. Exactly, and we'll see that the רגל Regel
point is not so much based on the issue of the greater
care people show on the רגל, Regel, it's based on חז"ל's Chazal
desire to create a sense of unity among the people on the
רגל. Regel. But, you know, it's an excellent point. Like, here's something
that clearly was handled before the רגל Regel and nevertheless has that
assumption. Yeah. If the rabbis put these restrictions on about who can
be trusted, they can waive them. Well, that's basically what I'm saying,
exactly. All right, again, question to me whether the rabbis were the
ones that invented these restrictions, but they're certainly the ones that are
coming to modify them. Okay. ואם אמר הפרשתי לתוכה רביעית קודש נאמן.
V’im amar hifrash’ti l’tochah revi’is kodesh ne’eman. And here's an again the
guy says he brings you your barrel of wine and it's not
during the times of the pressing. So, you know, I really can't
take it now because I can't assume that it’s... of course, if
you were to have separated out from that a little wine to
make it for נסכים nesachim for קודש, kodesh, then because... then I
would be able to believe you about the wine because you always
believe them about קודש, kodesh, and then I could believe you about
the rest of the barrel as well because it's all connected. Oh,
so that works. Okay, wink and a nod. So the גמרא Gemara
says like this, תנן התם, T’nan hatam, so we taught over there:
מודים בית שמאי ובית הלל שבודקין לעושי פסח ואין בודקין לאוכלי תרומה.
Modim Beis Shammai u’Beis Hillel she’bodkin l’osei Pesach v’ein bodkin l’ochlei terumah.
That they agree that you check for people who are going to
bring their פסח, Pesach, בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, but not for people
who are going to eat תרומה. terumah. מאי בודקין? Mai bodkin? What
are you checking? So אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל מנפח אדם בית
הפרס והולך. Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel menapei’ach adam beis hapras v’holeich.
So you basically have a field that has a grave that was
plowed over there and has possibly little bits of bone in the
field, and that's considered rabbinically you’re not allowed to walk through that
field or you’ll become טמא. tamei. And but you have to cross
through that field in order to get to ירושלים Yerushalayim to bring
your קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. Or you have to cross through that
field, I don’t know, to get home and eat your תרומה, terumah,
whatever the case is. So can you... is there a way you
can cross through that field? So they say what you do is
you like blow, it’s sort of like, you know, like clearing the
field for mines. So you blow the area right in front of
you, so it would blow away any little chips of bone on
the surface and then you take a step, then you blow the
area in front of you and you take a step. So you
can do that if you have to cross that field to eat
your קרבן פסח korban Pesach and you’re considered to be טהור. tahor.
Blowing with your...
your mouth, you’re walking across a field blowing...
step.
You better start... you better start עושי פסח. osei Pesach. Okay, fine.
All right, we’ve seen this before.
Yeah, this comes up... this comes up a number of times. Okay.
So, okay. So you can do that for פסח, Pesach, it’s more
urgent for פסח Pesach obviously. If you don’t bring your פסח Pesach
now, you’re going to blow it. And תרומה, terumah, you know, there’s
no urgency, so אוי, oy, you know what? I wasn't even thinking
about that. תרומה terumah there’s no urgency. Okay, so they don’t allow
this for תרומה. terumah. Okay. ורבי חייא בר אבא משמיה דעולא אמר
בית הפרס שנידוש טהור. V’Rabbi Chiya bar Abba mishmeih d’Ula amar beis
hapras shenidash tahor. Here’s another assumption
that you can make... עושי פסח. osei Pesach. For if you’re doing
your פסח Pesach and people have walked a path through this field
already and you can see that it’s been trampled down, right, the
earth has been like pressed down by people’s walking, then because it’s
been pre-tread, that somehow allows you to assume that there're no real
chips of bone that are left in that path.
I don’t know why being pre-tread makes you allow you to assume
that because it’s not necessarily true that the people who walked cared
about טומאה, tumah, you know, maybe they weren't כהנים kohanim and whatever,
but right, for some reason the fact that they tread it makes
us assume that somehow the chips of bone have been dislodged off
of that tread. Again, it’s only לעושי פסח. l’osei Pesach. If... if
for the purpose that you need to cross through that field to
bring your קרבן פסח. korban Pesach. But the other people bringing their
קרבן פסח korban Pesach too. Oh, that’s maybe... that’s good maybe. Okay,
so... so if you’re doing it for פסח Pesach again you can
be lenient either by blowing or if there’s a path that’s been
tread. לא העמידו דבריהם במקום כרת. Lo he’emidu divreihem b’makom kares. They
did not put their position up to prevent you from, you know,
bringing a פסח Pesach which otherwise you’d be liable כרת. kares. They
didn’t make their restrictions something that... that stands in the way of
you possibly being liable כרת. kares. אבל לאוכלי תרומה, Aval l’ochlei terumah,
but to prevent you from eating תרומה, terumah, they did say... העמידו
דבריהם במקום מיתה. He’emidu divreihem b’makom misah. They... they had their position,
you know, they erected their position, they kept it, because to prevent
you from eating תרומה terumah when you are טומאת מת, tumas meis,
which is a חיוב מיתה. chiyuv misah. Now, it’s not exactly the
same... it’s a weird parallel because by the פסח, Pesach, you’re חייב
כרת chayav kares if you don’t bring the פסח. Pesach. By תרומה,
terumah, you’re חייב מיתה בידי שמים chayav misah bidei Shamayim if you
eat the תרומה terumah when you’re טמא, tamei, if you do it.
So it’s like funny, it’s like: we wanted you to be able
to do the פסח Pesach and if... you know, otherwise you’d be
חייב כרת, chayav kares, so we had to move out of the
way to let you do the פסח, Pesach, we didn't want you
to get כרת. kares. But we are preventing you, you know, in
the case of the תרומה, terumah, not like now you’re going to
be חייב מיתה, chayav misah, we’re preventing you because thatll protect you
from being חייב מיתה. chayav misah. So it’s the same point, we
don’t want you to be חייב כרת, chayav kares, we don’t want
you to be חייב מיתה, chayav misah, but it's a funny way
it's structured in this parallel. Yes, but this the idea is one
of נאמנות, ne’emanus, you know, that... that you... If the idea is
one of נאמנות, neemanus, you know, that you relax the principles of
נאמנות neemanus in general, yes, then first of all I withdraw what
I said before about other people use that passage at the end,
but the idea is that you rely on other people in
general. Right. So, you're on that path. So the reliability is very
specific, meaning the reliability that we've been talking about, right, is around
oh I see you're thinking because פסח Pesach is a time of
the רגל regel and so on. Yeah the גמרא Gemara let's see
why the גמרא Gemara brings this in. The גמרא Gemara has not
brought this in to the assumption that the reliability that we've been
talking about about whether the food is טמא tamei or not, you
know, translates into a general reliability about other things. Like if you
come into, I don't know, like let's say it happens to be
the רגל regel and you know, I don't know, I mean there
are other types of Right. But you shouldn't make the distinction
between תרומה Terumah and פסח Pesach though, because for both of those
things relating to טומאה, tumah, it's not a question of you know
is it חייבי כרת, chayavei kares, חומרא, chumra, or כרת kares or
whatever, it's all about the נאמנות neemanus on this kind of דרבנן.
d'rabbanan. Right, but this is seen as more of an overrider, a
leniency let's say in נאמנות. neemanus. Right, you're the one blowing the
path. I mean, it's true the נידות niddos has to do with
other people, but I don't think the נידות niddos is because you
assume other people blew it. I think it assumes the natural process
of treading somehow dislodges the bone, though I don't really understand that.
But this really is not based on נאמנות. neemanus. In the first
case clearly not, it's about blowing. This is פסח, Pesach, do we
allow this leniency, you know, it's you know to this way of
assuming that this will address the טומאה tumah problems, it's a leniency,
do we allow it for this type of overriding concern? Yeah. You're
only חייב כרת chayav kares on פסח Pesach if you're within a
day of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Right. But they don't mention any That's a
good point, it's you're right. It's more like the category of חייב
כרת, chayav kares, you should also say you can bring a פסח
שני. Pesach Sheini. Anyway, let's take a look. Let's see let's try
to figure out what the גמרא Gemara is doing with it. איבעיא
להו, Ibaiya lehu, they asked a question. בודק לפסחו מהו שיאכל בתרומתו.
Bodek l'pischo mahu she-yochal b'terumaso. This is where it becomes more a
little more relevant and we'll see why it's bringing it in. So
you went ahead and you blew this path and walked through and
brought your קרבן פסח, Korban Pesach, and now I want to eat
my תרומה. Terumah. Okay, so what can I do? Can I assume
I'm also טהור tahor for תרומה Terumah purposes? It'd be a little
absurd to say I'm טהור tahor to bring the קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach but when I want to eat תרומה Terumah I have to
assume I'm טמא. tamei. Okay, but that's the question they're asking and
now we're going to see why it brought it in. But they
compare כרת kares to מיתה בידי שמים misa biydei shamayim which is
what I understand,
but it's also like can we can you give me a double
a different status for different things? So let's take a look. So
עולא אמר בודק לפסחו מותר לאכול בתרומתו. Ulla amar bodek l'pischo mutar
l'echol b'terumaso. If you walked through this path by the blowing and
you can bring your פסח, Pesach, then you're טהור, tahor, you can
eat your תרומה. Terumah. רבה בר עולא אמר בודק לפסחו אסור לאכול
בתרומתו, Rabbah bar Ulla amar bodek l'pischo assur l'echol b'terumaso, you can't.
אמר ליה ההוא סבא לא תפלוג עליה דעולא, Amar lei hahu saba
lo tiflog alei d'Ulla, so a certain elder said to Rabbah, don't
argue on עולא Ulla who says if you're good for one it's
good for the other. דתנן כוותיה, d'tenan kevasei, our משנה mishna supports
him. Our משנה mishna says אם אמר הפרשתי לתוכה רביעית קודש נאמן,
im amar hifrashti l'socha revi'is kodesh ne'eman, that if he said that
I took a little, you know, a little glass of wine out
of that barrel and I made it קודש, kodesh, then then he's
believed about the whole barrel of wine since he's believed on the
little glass that's going to be for נסכים. nesachim. So why don't
we say, no, you know, he's believed on the קודש kodesh one,
he's not believed on the rest of the barrel. But we don't
say that. אמר מדמהימן אקודש מהימן נמי אתרומה. Amar mi-d'meheiman a-kodesh meheiman
nami a-terumah. If you're believed for one, you're believed for the other.
הכא נמי מדמהימן אפסח מהימן נמי אתרומה, Hacha nami mi-d'meheiman a-Pesach meheiman
nami a-terumah, here because he's believed now this isn't use somebody else's
belief since he is trusted that the blowing did a sufficient job
for the purposes of פסח, Pesach, מהימן נמי אתרומה, meheiman nami a-terumah,
it also works for תרומה. Terumah. We're not going to say you're
you know the same person is טהור tahor for one thing and
טמא tamei for another, okay? In the same way the same barrel
of wine isn't going to be טהור tahor for taking קודש kodesh
out of it but טמא tamei for תרומה. Terumah. All right, so
that's that's what that was brought in to illustrate those things and
there's no response, it makes a lot of sense. Okay, כדי יין
וכדי שמן, kadi yan v'kadi shemen, the last one, okay, which is
barrels of wine and of oil, which are מדומעות, meduma'os, which normally
means some type of a mix of תרומה Terumah and חולין, chullin,
could also mean טבל, tevel, normally means a mix of תרומה Terumah
and חולין. chullin. They're believed on them at the time of the
גתות gitos and beforehand seventy days. Okay, so that's very bizarre. Why
what is the status of מדומעות meduma'os and why does it have
a special status? Let's take a look. תנא אין נאמנים לא על
הקנקנים ולא על התרומה. Tana: Ein ne'emanim lo al ha-kankanin v'lo al
ha-terumah. So they're not believed, not relating to the actual barrels themselves,
the jugs themselves, and not on the תרומה. Terumah. So what does
this mean? The גמרא Gemara says like this. אה במאי, Ah, b'mai,
what are we talking about? אי קנקנים דקודש, Ei kankanin d'kodesh, if
we're talking about like jugs that have in it wine or oil
that they sanctified, you know, for בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash purposes, מיגו
דמהימן אקודש מהימן נמי אקנקנים, migo d'meheiman a-kodesh meheiman nami a-kankanim, it
sort of goes to that same thing we said before about it
all being interrelated, although we'll see later times when we don't say
that, but for now, if you're going to believe them that the
wine in the jug is טהור, tahor, they're going to believe them
that the jug is טהור. tahor. אלא אקנקנים דתרומה, Ella, a-kankanim d'terumah,
so they're not believed about the jugs of תרומה. Terumah. פשיטא, Pshita,
of course you're not believed if it's not a special. if it's
not the שעת הגתות, sha'as hagittos, if it's not the special time,
of course you're not believed on the jugs. השתא Hasha תרומה לא
מהימן, truma lo mehemen, if you're not believed on the תרומה truma
itself, הקנקנים מהימן? hakankanim mehemen? Why would you be believed on the
jugs? So what's the scenario where you're not believed on the jugs
but he says לא על הקנקנים ולא על התרומה? lo al hakankanim
velo al hatruma? So if it's not the תרומה, truma, presumably we're
talking about not the time of the גתות. gittos. So of course
not on the קנקנים. kankanim. So when is there ever something special
to be said about the jugs? אלא בריקנים דקודש, Ella berikannim dekodesh,
we're talking about empty jugs and they're jugs you normally use to
put your קודש kodesh wine and oil in, but it happens to
be right now it's empty ובשאר ימות השנה u'vishar yemos hashana and
the rest of the year. So the rest of the year if
I tell you this wine is קודש, kodesh, it's טהור, tahor, you
believe me even if I'm an עם הארץ. am ha'aretz. Okay, and
if I brought it in a jug, you'd believe that the jug
is טהור. tahor. That's what the גמרא Gemara says, it's all, you
can't say one without the other. Okay, but if this is the
jug that I normally use for my קודש kodesh wine, and right
now it doesn't have קודש kodesh wine in it and you're the
חבר chaver and you want to borrow my jug, and I say,
"Sure, I tell you what, I'll even let you use my jug
that I use for my קודש kodesh wine and you can use
it and borrow it," you would have to still טובל tovel it
to the מקוה mikva because even though you believe me that it's
טהור tahor when the קודש kodesh wine was in it, right now
when it's only about the jug, you have to assume it's טמא.
tamei. Okay, so that's בריקנים דקודש berikannim dekodesh ובשאר ימות השנה. u'vishar
yemos hashana. That's when you don't believe them about their jugs. Now
ובמלאים דתרומה ובשעת הגתות. u'vimalaim detrume u'visha'as hagittos. Now there could even
be a time where you believe them about the תרומה truma and
not about the jugs, and this is ironic. You go ahead and
right, you have a jug filled with תרומה, truma, you believe me
that the תרומה truma is טהור, tahor, you believe me because it's
the time of the pressing, but you don't believe me about the
jug. So you're going to go ahead and I'm going to bring
my, my, you know, here it is, my jug of wine to
you the כהן חבר Kohen chaver and give you my תרומה truma
and it's the time of the גתות gittos and you can believe
me that it's טהור, tahor, but you're going to say, "You know
what, why don't you just pour it into my vessel here, you
know, take your vessel back," okay, because you can't actually treat the
vessel as טהור, tahor, only the wine in it, which is of
course bizarre. How could the wine in it be טהור tahor and
the vessel be טמא? tamei? Okay, so that's just the fiction that
we live with, okay, which the גמרא Gemara initially assumed it's all
got to be the same, and here it's saying, "Not necessarily, we
can believe you on the wine without believing you on the vessel."
Okay, so if you take a look at רש"י Rashi just to
see רש"י Rashi spell this out about fifteen lines before the lines
get wide: ובמלאים דתרומה ובשעת הגתות u'vimalaim detrume u'visha'as hagittos שאף על
פי שלא גזרו על תרומתן בשעת הגתות משום הפסד כהנים חברים. she'af
al pi shelo gazru al trumasun bisha'as hagittos mishum hefsed Kohanim chaveirim.
Now here's רש"י'ס Rashi's point: he points out that if it's really
just based on the fact that everybody's being careful, then if everybody's
really being careful now, you're going to believe them on the wine,
you're going to believe them on the jugs, right? So now רש"י
Rashi gets to the policy issue, and it's a little self-serving policy
issue, so let's take a look. He says: שלא גזרו על תרומתן
בשעת הגתות משום הפסד כהנים חברים דנמצא מפסיד את רוב תרומת ארץ
ישראל. shelo gazru al trumasun bisha'as hagittos mishum hefsed Kohanim chaveirim denimtza
mafsid es rov trumas Eretz Yisrael. So it's not just, "Oh, everybody
is really careful during this period of time." It's, "We've got to
make it מותר muttar during this period of time or all the
כהנים Kohanim are going to lose out on ninety percent of the
תרומה." truma. So, "Okay, now we'll believe you." Okay, that's only for
the wine, that's only for the stuff that they need. But על
הקנקנים לא הימינום דאין כהן חבר מקבל מהן קנקנים עם התרומה אבל
מערה הוא לכליו. al hakankanim lo heiminum dein Kohen chaver mekabel mehen
kankanim im hatruma aval me'ara hu l'keilav. Okay, so pour it into
my thing, but here it's quite fascinating that you really see and
we're going to see it again by the רגל, regel, that there
are certain policy considerations. Now the רגל regel is less self-serving. The
רגל regel is to create a sense of unity. This is to
ensure that the חברים chaverim get their share of the תרומה. truma.
Okay, and now presumably there are some facts to base it on.
People are more careful at the time of גתות, gittos, more careful
at the time of the רגל, regel, but you know what, at
the end of the day, these are the policy considerations and the
thing to make it understandable is that from the strict הלכה halacha
point of view, everybody would always be believed all the time. All
of this is just stringencies upon stringencies, so we're more at liberty
to waive it. But again, רש"י Rashi really makes clear the policy
issues here. Okay, so let's go back to the גמרא. Gemara. So
it says like this: ובמלאים דתרומה ובשעת הגתות. u'vimalaim detrume u'visha'as hagittos.
תנן Tnan ותנא משנה: utana mishna: כדי יין וכדי שמן המדומאות. kadei
yayin u'khadei shemen hameduma'os. So barrels of wine, barrels of oil that
are mixed, which we still don't really know what that means. מאי
לאו מדומאות דתרומה? Mai lav meduma'os detrume? Does it not mean that
they are mixed with תרומה? truma? So meaning that they have תרומה
truma in it and it says that the כדין kadim are also
believed. It says the barrels, right, or the pitchers of wine and
oil. That's the point of the משנה, mishna, not just the wine
and oil. The language is כדי יין וכדי שמן נאמנים עליהם, kadei
yayin u'khadei shemen ne'emanim aleihem, right? So that's what the משנה mishna
said. It said first it says the wine you're believed בשעת הגתות
bisha'as hagittos and the כדין, kadim, the pitchers, you're believed even seventy
days before. Okay, so here it's explicit for God's sakes, you're believed
on the... the pitchers even seventy days before, certainly at the time
of the גתות. gatot. Why are you telling me you're not believed
on the vessels? So doesn't it mean that it has תרומה Terumah
in it and even anything that's going to have תרומה Terumah in
it or going to be used for תרומה Terumah you're believed even
seventy days before? So the גמרא Gemara says, אמי דבי רבי חייא,
Ami devei Rabbi Chiyya, no, מדומעות לקודש. medumaot lekodesh. No, it means
stuff that you're going to use for קודש kodesh purposes. Okay, and
that's why it's going you're believed on them even about the big
jugs themselves. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי איכא דמוע לקודש? umi
ika demua lekodesh? When we talk about a mix for קודש, kodesh,
a mix for תרומה Terumah might mean טבל. tevel. So מדומעות לתרומה
medumaot le-Terumah might mean that I'm using pitchers, it isn't yet the
time of pressing, but I'm using them for my grapes. My grapes
aren't yet תרומה, Terumah, but they're מדומעות לתרומה medumaot le-Terumah because they're
going to be תרומה Terumah is going to be separated from them.
So meaning that would be a way of saying all the types
of vessels I'm going to be using for this stuff that תרומה
Terumah is going to come out of, so the same way I'm
believed about the תרומה, Terumah, I'm even believed about the vessels that
I'm using with the olives and the grapes that have the pre-תרומה
Terumah mixed into them effectively because it's טבל. tevel. Okay, that makes
a lot of sense, but that would tell me that I'd be
believed about the vessels, but you said I'm not believed about the
vessels. So they say, okay, we're talking not about תרומה, Terumah, we're
talking about קודש. kodesh. So what does דמוע demua mean in the
context of קודש? kodesh? So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי איכא דמוע
לקודש? umi ika demua lekodesh? אמי דבי רבי אילא, Ami devei Rabbi
Ila, במטהר חביתו ליטול הימנו נסכים. bimtaher chavito litol himenu nesachim. Yes,
because what it means is is that I have declared my intention
that I am going to be taking wine for נסכים nesachim out
of what we're going to be pressing, the wine we're going to
be pressing. So here we are, we're harvesting all the grapes, I
make an announcement: Guys, I want everybody to be super careful, עם
הארץ, am haaretz, I want everyone to be super careful because, we're
anyway careful this time, but let's be super careful because I'm going
to be using some of this wine to bring my נסכים nesachim
from. I've declared my intention, so these grapes are seen to have
potential, or like not potential, like pre, you know, separated out קודש,
kodesh, and therefore because that's their status you can even believe the
status of the vessels that are used, not just the status of
the wine. Okay, so that's a really hard read in the משנה.
Mishnah. Let's just admit that the פשט pshat of the משנה Mishnah
is that you're believed on the vessels more than the wine. The
wine you're only believed בשעת הגתות, bishas hagatot, and the vessels you're
believed even seventy days before. Why do you think by the way
you'd be believed in the vessels before you begin to be believed
about the wine? You have to prepare the vessels ahead of time.
Okay, so that's the simple sense of the משנה. Mishnah. But since
the גמרא Gemara says that you're not believed on the vessels for
תרומה, Terumah, only on the wine, only on the actual, you know,
sort of food, it has to go ahead and make it a
special case of קודש, kodesh, not a case of תרומה. Terumah. And
now let's just look at this idea that the belief of the
vessels begins seventy days before. So קודם לגיתו שבעים יום. kodem legito
shivim yom. אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, שמע מינה, shma mina, דינא הוא,
dina hu, דעל אריסי למיטרח גופני, de-al arisei lemitrach gofni, שבעים יומי
מקמי דמזדבנא. shivim yomei mikamei de-mizdavna. Seventy days before the actual time
of the harvest. It says if you're believed seventy days before, it
means that the normal practice is to start preparing everything already—that's a
long time, like two months before the actual period of the harvest.
Okay, so that's the issue of belief on the vessels as opposed
to just the wine, but given the גמרא Gemara that you're not
believed on it, we really highlight, as רש"י Rashi points out, the
policy considerations that are at play here in terms of believing people
about the תרומה. Terumah. Yes. The further we go in this, the
more
it seems like this is Bizarro Talmud. Yes. What's this idea that
so because you announce that—what category is that? Because you announce that
I'm going to take הקדש hekdesh from this thing, it's like—what's this
principle? It doesn't appear anywhere. Right. I agree. I mean, I made
it a little simplified because it says מטהר חביתו, metaher chavito, which
means like I'm actually going through and keep—saying—trying to do some practice,
like like, you know, I'm not just stating it, but I'm saying
and let's be really careful now that we dunk it in the
מקוה, mikveh, you know, we realize that we're going to be using
it for קודש. kodesh. But still, like, that's a novelty. I understand.
Yes. I agree. I agree. It is—it is. All right. So now,
next משנה. Mishnah. And now we're sort of coming into where we're
circling in on where we do away with these distinctions. So we
have קודש kodesh in general in Judea, we've got תרומה Terumah at
the time of the pressing and maybe the—and the issue of the
vessels is a little different. And now we get to places near
ירושלים Yerushalayim at all times of the year around—this is about vessels.
We're now on vessels for a moment before we get back to
food. מן המודיעים ולפנים, min ha-Modiin ulefanim, from מודיעים, Modiin, which is
a place about it says fifteen מיל mil outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
which is about fifteen kilometers. Okay. So which is a significant place,
it's like where you could get to ירושלים Yerushalayim in, you know,
in a day or in a half a day.
So it's in the immediate environs of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Depending on the traffic, you say. נאמנים על כלי חרס.
neemanim al kilei cheres. that you are believed, עמי הארץ Amei Ha'aretz
are believed that the pottery vessels are טהור tahor at all times.
Why is that? So we're going to say that they did not
make kilns in ירושלים Yerushalayim for making pottery because that would have
smelled up ירושלים Yerushalayim and even then they had air pollution rules
or whatever, so the kilns were always outside of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay,
which means you're putting them outside of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so you're also
putting them in the area where the more like where the villagers
and the more עמי הארץ Amei Ha'aretz are presumably and therefore you've
got to come up with a more lenient policy to believe people
for the for the sake of the people in ירושלים, Yerushalayim, you've
got to be able to believe the people at in the outskirts
of ירושלים Yerushalayim who are the ones making the pottery vessels. Okay,
so there we actually again a policy consideration we're going to believe
them because people need pottery vessels and they are not able to
make them themselves, they're being made on the outskirts, you know, in
ירושלים Yerushalayim in the industrial area or whatever and that's where you'll
have the עם הארץ Am Ha'aretz who are making it. So if
you look at רש"י Rashi again in terms of the policy, five
lines down in the wide lines, רש"י Rashi says: ולפיכך האמינום שלא
לגזור עליהם שאין גוזרין גזירה על הציבור שאין רוב הציבור יכולים לעמוד
בה. Ulefikhach he'eminum shelo ligzor aleihem she'en gozrin gezeirah al hatzibbur she'en
rov hatzibbur yekholim la'amod bah. If you told people you couldn't trust
the people who are making the pottery vessels, nobody would be able
to live with that, you need to be able to buy pottery
vessels. All right, so we'll trust them about the pottery vessels. Okay,
now we're going to see later that it's about like the small
and the thin vessels, not the big heavy ones because the small
and the thin ones are the more daily use vessels where there's
more of a need and therefore they gave them you know blanket
believability. מן המודיעין ולחוץ, Min haModi'in velachutz, if however it's from מודיעין
Modi'in away from ירושלים, Yerushalayim, אין נאמנים, en ne'emanin, they're not believed.
כיצד Keitzad how is this? הקדר שהוא מוכר קדירות, Hakaddar shehu mokher
kederot, you have a you know a jug merchant who's selling his
jugs, נכנס לפנים ממודיעין, nichnas lifnim mimodin, you're going to like this
Dov because this both of you Dovs I guess for whatsoever but
anyway because this is the absurdity that it's telling you explicitly. The
same guy, here's the guy with the jugs on his back with
his donkey, whatever his wagon filled with jugs, נכנס לפנים ממודיעין, nichnas
lifnim mimodin, he's now you find and you bump into him and
he's in and he's in from מודיעין Modi'in towards ירושלים, Yerushalayim, הוא
הקדר והן הקדירות והן הלוקחים נאמן, hu hakaddar vehan kederot vehan halokchim
ne'eman, the same seller, the same jugs, the same buyers, נאמן, ne'eman,
you can buy it. יצא Yatza if the if the same guy
with the same jugs and the same sellers you happen to bump
into him outside of מודיעין, Modi'in, אינו נאמן, eno ne'eman, he's not
believed. So here the משנה Mishna spells out to you the pure
formalism of this. We gotta have rules and you know these are
the rules, you can't go ahead and check every case individually, these
are the rules and this is how it works. Okay, it's like
an off of a price drop this part on 47th street because,
hey, right exactly. Okay, תנא מודיעין פעמים כלפנים ופעמים כלחוץ. Tanna Modi'in
pe'amim kelifnim upe'amim kelachutz. How about מודיעין Modi'in itself? Right, you said
from inside מודיעין Modi'in and outside מודיעין, Modi'in, what about מודיעין Modi'in
itself? What's its status? So sometimes it's like the inside and sometimes
the outside. This is going to get really weird. כיצד Keitzad how
is this possible? קדר יוצא וחבר נכנס כלפנים. Kaddar yotze vechaver nichnas
kelifnim. If the jug merchant is going away from ירושלים Yerushalayim and
the חבר chaver is going towards ירושלים, Yerushalayim, so this is the
last opportunity, right, here's ירושלים, Yerushalayim, here's מודיעין. Modi'in. Okay, מודיעין, Modi'in,
okay, now if you are the חבר chaver and you're heading away
from ירושלים Yerushalayim and he's the קדר kaddar and he's planning on
going towards oh, it's the other way around first. קדר יוצא, Kaddar
yotze, sorry, so you're the קדר kaddar and you're in מודיעין Modi'in
and you're going away and this guy is the חבר chaver and
he's heading towards ירושלים. Yerushalayim. So this is the last opportunity the
חבר chaver will have to buy the jugs from the קדר, kaddar,
right? Because he's going away and he's going towards. Okay, so since
it's the last opportunity they'll have to do it, we'll consider it
like it's in towards ירושלים Yerushalayim and he can buy the jugs.
Okay, קדר יוצא וחבר נכנס כלפנים. Kaddar yotze vechaver nichnas kelifnim. שניהם
נכנסים, Sheneihem nikhnasim, if they're both on the way towards ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
so don't buy it in מודיעין, Modi'in, wait till you get you
know in you know you know within מודיעין, Modi'in, wait till you
get you know you know within the inside, this is לפנים. lifnim.
Okay, so wait till you and this is לחוץ. lachutz. So wait
till you get into the לפנים lifnim section, don't do it in
מודיעין, Modi'in, get into the לפנים lifnim section, okay, because you're both
going in that direction anyway. Okay, just because you're both going in
that direction I don't know how it means you're necessarily traveling together
but okay. שניהם נכנסים Sheneihem nikhnasim או שניהם יוצאים כלחוץ. o sheneihem
yotze'im kelachutz. Now the interesting thing too although is that if you're
both heading out it's also כלחוץ, kelachutz, but that makes a little
bit of sense. Since you're on your way out even when you're
in מודיעין Modi'in we look at you more as away from ירושלים
Yerushalayim than we look at you as towards ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Okay, אמר
אביי, Amar Abbaye, אף אנן נמי תנינא. Af anan nami tanina. This
can also be inferred from the משנה Mishna which is going to
be a little bit interesting because we didn't see any of this
in the משנה, Mishna, let's take a look. הקדר שמכר קדרות... Hakaddar
shemakhar kederot... הקדר שמכר הקדרות ונכנס לפנים מן המודיעין. Hakadar shemachar hakedirot
venichnas lifnim min haModiin. It says the jug seller who is selling
them and is now found inside of מודיעין, Modiin, he's believed. Says
טעמא דלפנים מן המודיעין, taima delifnim min haModiin, that means that only
inside of מודיעין Modiin he's believed. המודיעין גופא, HaModiin gufah, in מודיעין
Modiin itself, לא מהימן, lo meheman, he's not believed. אימא סיפא, Ema
seifa, let's look at the end. יצא, Yatza, if he leaves away
outside of מודיעין, Modiin, אינו נאמן, eino ne'eman, he's not believed. המודיעין
גופא נאמן, HaModiin gufah ne'eman, it sounds like in מודיעין Modiin he
is believed. Right, the משנה Mishnah is not clear about מודיעין. Modiin.
So rather than saying the משנה Mishnah is being clear, we're going
to reconcile it. אלא לאו, Ela lav, it must depend on the
case. שמע מינה כאן בקדר יוצא וחבר נכנס, Shema mina kan bekadar
yotze vechaver nichnas, if the קדר kadar is going away and the
חבר chaver is going in, then מודיעין Modiin is like it's inside
and he is believed. כאן בשניהם יוצאים או שניהם נכנסים, Kan bishnehem
yotzim o shnehem nichnasim, if they're both leaving and they're or they're
both going, then it's considered on the outside. And the גמרא Gemara
accepts that: שמע מינה. shema mina. Oh, that's a good inference. I
guess you could have speculated it in a dozen other ways of
distinguishing, but that's what the גמרא Gemara is prepared to read that
in. Okay. Now we have a qualification of why believing them on
these vessels. I mentioned this already. תנא נאמנים על כלי חרס הדקים
לקודש, Tana ne'emanim al klei cheres hadakim lekodesh, they're believed on the
thin ones, on the small ones, to use them for קודש kodesh
purposes. So this is a double qualification. Okay. Basically they're the small
ones, not the large ones, because the small ones are the ones
that are more in demand and therefore we need to have greater
leniencies. Okay, and we'll see a little bit more about that. But
רבא Rava says that they're believed on it לקודש, lekodesh, which is
not totally clear what it means. רש״י Rashi doesn't really fully explicate
that. Does it mean even if you want to use it for
קודש kodesh purposes, or only if they claim that this is, you
know, because it's for קודש, kodesh, that gives them extra believability like
we saw a little bit before? Not exactly clear. But okay, let's
take a look. But the key thing that it's interesting, but certainly
the idea is only on the small ones, on the thin and
the small ones. אמר ריש לקיש והוא שניטלין בידו אחת, Amar Reish
Lakish vehu shenitlin beyado achat, they have to be so small that
you can basically carry them with one hand. ורבי יוחנן אמר אפילו
שאין ניטלין בידו אחת, VeRabbi Yochanan amar afilu she-ein nitlin beyado achat,
even if you basically need to use two hands. Maybe they're thin,
they're big, but they're thin. אמר ריש לקיש לא שנו אלא ריקנין
אבל מליאין לא. Amar Reish Lakish lo shanu ela reikanin aval meleim
lo. It's only if they're empty. If they're full, then not. Normally
before we thought that full was better because you could be believed
on what's inside. But here we'll be dealing with a case where
maybe it's not true. You know, they're let's say it's תרומה, trumah,
let's say inside is חולין. chulin. So they're not believed about חולין
chulin wine. They're, you know, they're not believed about תרומה trumah wine
not during the time of the גיתות. gitot. So basically if they're
selling you the jug with the wine in it, but it's not
תרומה, trumah, it's not קודש, kodesh, it's just חולין, chulin, you have
to assume the wine is טמא. tamei. Can when you're buying the
wine and assuming the wine is טמא, tamei, still assume the jug
is טהור? tahor? It's like the reverse of what we had before,
right? Before you bought the wine that was תרומה trumah at the
time of the pressing, you assumed the wine was טהור, tahor, but
you had to assume the jug was טמא. tamei. Here, because it's
a special believability about the vessels, it's about pottery vessels from מודיעין
דלפנים, Modiin delifnim, so we're talking the believability here specific to the
vessels. What if you have to assume the wine is טמא tamei
based on the normal rules? Would you be still allowed to assume
that the vessel is טהור? tahor? Okay. So ריש לקיש Reish Lakish
says it's only if they're empty. If they're full and you have
to assume the stuff in it is טמא, tamei, so you have
to assume that the vessel is טמא tamei too. ורבי יוחנן אמר
אפילו מליאין, VeRabbi Yochanan amar afilu meleim, even if it's the same
way that it was possible before to say the contradictory idea, right?
Before we said the תרומה trumah wine was טהור tahor and the
vessel was טמא. tamei. Here we're saying the wine is טמא tamei
and the vessel is טהור. tahor. Okay. So it says, ואפילו אפיקורסותו
לתוכה, ve-afilu apikorsuto letokhah, even if your heresy is inside it. No,
that's not what it means. אפיקורסותו Apikorsuto basically means like their undershirt
or something, but nobody exactly knows what what the point of saying
that is other than like just I don't know, some type of
a throwaway line. רש״י Rashi basically says even like filled with חולין
chulin wine. How that אפיקורסותו apikorsuto means that I don't know. ואמר
רבא, Ve-amar Rava, but anyway, even though the wine is טמא, tamei,
the vessel is טהור. tahor. ואמר רבא ומודה רבי יוחנן במשקין עצמן
שהן טמאים. Ve-amar Rava umodeh Rabbi Yochanan bemashkin atzman shehein tmeim. He's
not claiming that if it's full, that because the vessel is טהור
tahor the liquid is טהור. tahor. No. He's saying I can see
the liquid is טמא, tamei, it's חולין, chulin, he's not believed on
חולין, chulin, or it's תרומה trumah not at the time of the
גיתות. gitot. So the yeah, the liquid is טמא, tamei, but nevertheless,
the vessel is טהור. tahor. We're going to live with this contradiction.
ואל תתמה, Ve-al titmah, don't be astounded, right? Because obviously you should
be astounded, but don't be astounded. שהרי לוגין מלאי משקין, Sheharei lugin
melei mashkin, if you have pitchers or whatever filled with liquid, לוגין
טמאין טומאת שבעה ומשקין טהורין. lugin tmeim tumat shiva umashkin tehorin. You
can have the pitchers which are טמאים tmeim for seven days because
of מת, met, and the משקין טהורין. mashkin tehorin. You will remember
we had this before, that בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי,
Beit Shammai, right? The case about the house, right? That had the
dead body in it, right? And you had the כלי... kli... here,
and the second thing, right, remember that, and you had, you know,
some, and you had food here whatever, anyway, so basically what we
said was the טומאה tuma goes through because you have to assume
the חרס cheres is טמא, tame, but the עם הארץ am ha-aretz
won't believe won't listen to us and believe us, so we'll say
for the stuff that we're not going to handle that only the
עם הארץ am ha-aretz will use, like the food, that's טומאת שבעה.
tumat shiva. The stuff we have to buy... I'm sorry, that's טהור,
tahor, excuse me, because it's not going to affect us anyway. The
stuff we might use, like the vessels, that's going to be טומאת
שבעה. tumat shiva. So that's what it says, we have the same
thing, the vessel could be טומאת שבעה tumat shiva and the food
inside of it could be טהור. tahor. So here too the reverse,
the food, the wine could be טמא tame and the vessel could
be טהור. tahor. Okay, so we're getting into some crazy ideas. But
what we're actually but the larger theme that we're seeing is the
way the policy issues about making sure כהנים חברים kohanim chaverim get
their fair share of the תרומה, terumah, making sure people have pottery
vessels, right, making sure that people don't run off the דרך derech
and abandon us because they don't have access to the בית המקדש
Beis HaMikdash because of all these various types of considerations we're going
to believe people even if normally we wouldn't believe them or because
of stringencies we wouldn't believe them. And we're going to finally get
to the idea where this is all leading, which is in the
רגל regel is the big policy consideration that everybody's believed about everything.
Okay, let's just try to read one more section here. See if
we can get this one quickly. הגבאים שנכנסו ha-gabba'im she-nichnesu tax collectors
that came into the house לתוך הבית le-toch ha-bayis and they came
to maybe see some property because you're behind in your taxes. וכן
הגנבים שהחזירו את הכלים ve-chen ha-ganavim she-hechziru es ha-keilim or let's say
thieves came into your house and then they stole stuff but then
they did תשובה, teshuvah, yeah, that's appropriate for ערב יום כיפור Erev
Yom Kippur and they're returning the stuff. נאמנים לומר לא נגענו. ne'emanim
lomar lo naganu. So they're the tax collectors are believed to say
we you know we didn't touch these vessels, maybe we touched these
we didn't touch those, you believe them and the ones they didn't
touch you assume the tax collectors are the עמי הארץ. am-ei ha-aretz.
Remember Jesus is eating with the tax collectors. These are the עמי
הארץ, am-ei ha-aretz, the people you don't eat with, the people you
keep separate from. Okay, anyway, but they're believed to say what they
touched and what they didn't touch so you don't have to worry
about the stuff that they didn't touch. Similarly, the גנב ganav comes
and he returns the vessels, a) maybe you believe him that even
though I stole these vessels I didn't touch the other ones, or
maybe even the vessels he's returning he's believed to say he didn't
touch let's say the wine inside of it. Let's say it's a
pottery vessel that if you don't touch the inside you don't make
it טמא. tame. So they're all believed, amazing, even the people, גנבים,
ganavim, tax collectors, people you generally wouldn't believe about this stuff, they
are believed. ובירושלים u-vi-Yerushalayim and in ירושלים Yerushalayim נאמנים על הקודש. ne'emanim
al ha-kodesh. People now this is no longer tax collectors. In ירושלים
Yerushalayim people are believed about קודש. kodesh. I mean we also saw
in general in יהודה Yehudah they're believed about קודש. kodesh. And here's
the point that I've been
telling you ובשעת הרגל u-vi-sha'as ha-regel at the time of the רגל
regel אף על התרומה af al ha-terumah everybody is believed even on
תרומה. terumah. Okay, so the thing about שעת הרגל sha'as ha-regel everybody
believed is like the big hugest thing about unifying the people, but
the tax collector thing comes first. Let's just read the גמרא Gemara
on the tax collectors and let's take a look. רמינהי. Remini. הגבאים
שנכנסו ha-gabba'im she-nichnesu we have a ברייתא beraisa that says a משנה
Mishnah that says the opposite. Tax collectors came into the house לתוך
הבית le-toch ha-bayis כולו טמא, kulo tame, you assume everything is טמא.
tame. Says לא קשיא. lo kashya. הא דאיכא נכרי בהדייהו הא דליכא
נכרי בהדייהו. ha de-ika nochri bahadeihu ha de-leika nochri bahadeihu. Is there
a non-Jew with them or not? If there's a non-Jew with them
and he's supervising or whatever, they're going to have to inspect all
of your various vessels, you know, so therefore you have to assume
they touched everything and they're not going to, you can't believe them.
But if there's not a non-Jew with them, then they'll be more
careful. דתנן de-tnan אם יש נכרי עמהם im yesh nochri imahem if
there is a non-Jew with them נאמנים לומר לא נכנסנו ne'emanim lomar
lo nichnasnu they can say we didn't go into the house because
you know they wouldn't make that up. אבל אין נאמנים לומר נכנסנו
אבל לא נגענו. aval ein ne'emanim lomar nichnasnu aval lo naganu. They
can't say we went in and we did not touch, right, רש"י
Rashi explains why because רש"י Rashi says אין נאמנים לומר לא נגענו
דמירתת אם לא יחפשו כל הבית. ein ne'emanim lomar lo naganu de-mirtas
im lo yechapsu kol ha-bayis. Not because the non-Jew will make them
lie to say they didn't touch but because you have to assume
that if there was a non-Jew there they inspected everything because they
didn't want to get in trouble, you know, with the supervisor. Right,
basically. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says אבל אין נאמנים לומר נכנסנו
אבל לא נגענו. aval ein ne'emanim lomar nichnasnu aval lo naganu. וכי
איכא נכרי בהדייהו מאי הוי? ve-chi ika nochri bahadeihu mai havei? Who
cares, why does it make a difference? רבי יוחנן ורבי אלעזר. Rabbi
Yochanan ve-Rabbi Elazar. חד אמר אימת נכרי עליהם chad amar eimas nochri
aleihem they're afraid of him. וחד אמר אימת מלכות עליהם ve-chad amar
eimas malchus aleihem he represents the government and they're afraid he's going
to report to the government that they didn't do a good enough
job. So מאי בינייהו mai beineihu who cares if it's him or
him reporting? איכא בינייהו ika beineihu נכרי שאינו חשוב nochri she-eino chashuv
that he's not such an important guy, so they're not afraid of
him. But are they still have to afraid that he might report
on them? That's just another עם הארץ am ha-aretz who's supervising them,
so that presumably would they then they wouldn't have to do everything
they wouldn't have to check out everything. You know it's their fellow
Jew they'll be a little easygoing, they won't do a... but a
non-Jew he's going to make them, you know, do. Let's just read
the one thing about the גנבים. ganavim. From the next משנה. Mishnah.
We have to stop. We do, it says 8:30 here. 8:28. וכן
הגנבים שהחזירו את הכלים. ve-chen ha-ganavim she-hechziru es ha-keilim. So the גמרא
Gemara says... רמינו, Ram'inu, that you believe in גנבים ganavim that are
returning things? You're right. My thing is fast. רמינו. Ram'inu. I'll ask
you on this. הגנבים שנכנסו לתוך הבית אינו טמא אלא מקום דריסת
רגלי הגנבים. Haganavim shenichnesu l'toch habayit eino tamei ela mekom drisat raglei
haganavim. It's only טמא tamei where they're walking, but so that it's
not clear what the question is. Why is that a problem? It's
only where they walked is טמא. tamei. But רש״י Rashi assumes that
the question is, if where they walk you have to assume is
טמא, tamei, then maybe you have to assume that the vessels that
they handled are טמא tamei and you can't—they can't tell you they
didn't touch the stuff inside the vessel. Not so clear what the
question is. Let's see what the answer is. אמר רב פנחס משמיה
דרב או משמיה דרבא, Amar Rav Pinchas mishmei deRav o mishmei deRava,
anyway it's an important answer for every ערב יום כיפור. Erev Yom
Kippur. כשיעשו תשובה, Keshe'asu teshuvah, ah, when they did תשובה, teshuvah, then
because they're returning the vessels, then you believe them. Because they're doing—they're
returning the vessels, they're doing תשובה. teshuvah. But when they didn't do
תשובה, teshuvah, then you have to assume that wherever they might have
touched was טמא. tamei. Okay, דיקא נמי דקתני שהחזירו את הכלים. Deika
nami diktani shehechziru et hakelim. It says they returned the כלים. kelim.
שמע מינה. Shema mina. That is a good point. Okay, so now
the question here is, by the way, what isn't explored is, why
do you believe these people? Like you normally don't believe them about
things like קודש Kodesh and תרומה Terumah and so on. Why do
you believe them? Like, whatever. So רש״י Rashi says it's only about
קודש. Kodesh. And it goes back to the point that you believe
עם הארץ Am ha'aretz about קודש. Kodesh. תוספות Tosafot says it's even
about תרומה. Terumah. And maybe there's a difference between believing them on
their own stuff and believing them on your stuff. Like maybe, you
know, for my own stuff—I understand that you're a חבר, chaver, and
I'm not going to tell you, you know, and I know you
care about this or whatever, I'm not going to tell you that
I did or didn't touch when it's not true, it's your stuff.
But my stuff, you know, what I believe I've done correctly with
my stuff, maybe I'll, you know, interpret those facts differently than if
you're asking me about how I handled your stuff. And it's true,
you know, I mean sometimes it's the reverse. How do we handle
other people's property as opposed to how we handle our own? Some—sometimes
some people are more careful with other people's property, other people are
more sloppy with other people's property. But that is interesting. But רש״י
Rashi limits it to קודש. Kodesh. Okay, you know what? I am
going to end here because we will start after יום כיפור Yom
Kippur and we'll read how כל ישראל Kol Yisrael comes together on
the רגל regel as a proper lead-in to סוכות. Sukkot. So that's
what we're going to pick up with מוצאי יום כיפור. Motza'ei Yom
Kippur. Everybody should have an easy and a meaningful fast. Normal time
on Sunday. Normal time on Sunday.